# William Blair

GraalVM Oracle Labs Washington, D.C. U.S.A.

url: https://wdblair.io associations: ACM, IEEE google scholar

#### **Current Position**

Senior Member of Technical Staff, Oracle Labs

### Research Interests

I am interested in developing novel program analysis techniques and defenses for cyber-security. I currently investigate this topic on the Graal platform team within Oracle Labs, where I work on control-flow integrity (CFI), language and runtime fuzz testing, intraprocess isolation, and software supply chain security. During my PhD, I explored how binary analysis tools can inform runtime monitors for microservices. I investigated this cloud security topic while interning in the Cyber Security Intelligence (CSI) team at IBM Research where I participated in the DARPA Cyber-Hunting at Scale (CHASE) program. I used memory protection keys (MPKs) available in recent Intel CPUs to improve applications' memory safety. This was done as a part of the NSF Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace (SaTC) Taming Memory Corruption with Security Monitors program.

Earlier in my PhD, I worked on *micro-fuzzing*, a novel fuzz testing technique to detect algorithmic complexity (AC) vulnerabilities in production Java programs and libraries during the DARPA Space and Time Analysis for Cybersecurity (STAC) program. The micro-fuzzing prototype, HotFuzz, has detected previously unknown vulnerabilities in the Java Runtime Environment (JRE) which were confirmed by Oracle and IBM. HotFuzz has also found bugs in widely used Java libraries, including org.json.

### Education

2014-2023

PhD in Computer Science, Boston University

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Software Security Vulnerabilities Through Secure Environment

Programming

Advisors: Manuel Egele, Hongwei Xi

2012-2014 MS in Computer Science, Boston University

Project: Dependent Types for Real Time Constraints

Advisor: Hongwei Xi

2008-2012 BA in Computer Science, Boston University

### **Publications**

William Blair, Frederico Araujo, Teryl Taylor, Jiyong Jang. Automated Synthesis of Effect Graph Policies for Microservice-Aware Stateful System Call Specialization. In Proceedings of the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (Oakland), San Francisco, CA, US, May 2024.

Mark Lemay, Qiancheng Fu, William Blair, Cheng Zhang, Hongwei Xi. A Dependently Typed Language with Dynamic Equality. In Proceedings of the ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on Type-Driven Development (TyDE), Seattle, WA, US, September 2023.

William Blair, William Robertson, Manuel Egele. ThreadLock: Native Principal Isolation Through Memory Protection Keys. In Proceedings of the ACM ASIA Conference on Computer and Communications Security (ASIACCS), Melbourne, VIC, Australia, July 2023.

William Blair, William Robertson, Manuel Egele. MPKAlloc: Efficient Heap Meta-Data Integrity Through Hardware Memory Protection Keys. In Proceedings of the Conference on Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA) Cagliari, Sardinia Italy, June 2022.

William Blair, Andrea Mambretti, Sajjad Arshad, Michael Weissbacher, William Robertson, Engin Kirda, Manuel Egele. HotFuzz: Discovering Temporal and Spatial Denial-of-Service Vulnerabilities Through Guided Micro-Fuzzing. In the ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS) April 2022.

Leila Delshadtehrani, Sadullah Canakci, William Blair, Manuel Egele, Ajay Joshi. FlexFilt: Towards Flexible Instruction Filtering for Security. In Proceedings of the Annual Computer Security Applications Conference (ACSAC) December 2021.

William Blair, Andrea Mambretti, Sajjad Arshad, Michael Weissbacher, William Robertson, Engin Kirda, Manuel Egele. HotFuzz: Discovering Algorithmic Denial-of-Service Vulnerabilities Through Guided Micro-Fuzzing. In Proceedings of the ISOC Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) San Diego, CA US, February 2020.

William Blair, Hongwei Xi. Dependent Types for Multi-Rate Data Flows in Synchronous Programming. In Post-Proceedings of the ACM ML/OCAML Workshop September 2015.

#### **Patents**

Matthias Neugschwandtner, William Blair. Method for control flow isolation with protection keys and indirect branch tracking. US Patent Application US17/882,007

Frederico Araujo, William Blair, Sanjeev Das, Jiyong Jang. Guided Micro-Fuzzing through Hybrid Program Analysis. US Patent 11,822,673

Frederico Araujo, William Blair, Teryl Paul Taylor. Stateful Microservice-Aware Intrusion Detection. US Patent 11,720,667 Frederico Araujo, Teryl Paul Taylor, Jiyong Jang, William Blair. Intrusion Detection in Micro-Services through Container Telemetry and Behavior Modeling. US Patent 11,748,473
Frederico Araujo, William Blair, Teryl Paul Taylor. Automated Synthesis of Reference Policies for Runtime Microservice Protection. US Patent Application 17/390,881

## Talks

2021	Symbolic Modeling of Micro Services for Intrusion Detection
	IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy Poster Session 2021
2021	Microservice-Aware Reference Monitoring through Hybrid Program Analysis
	FloCon 2021 at CMU Software Engineering Institute (SEI)
2019	HotFuzz: Finding Space and Time Vulnerabilities in Java Programs
	DARPA Space and Time Analysis for Cybersecurity P.I. Meeting
2016	Continuum: Finding Space and Time Vulnerabilities in Java Programs
	DARPA Space and Time Analysis for Cybersecurity P.I. Meeting
2016	Side Channels and Worst Case Behavior in Java
	Northeastern-WPI Seminar on Security
2015	Using a Portfolio of SMT Solvers in Software Development
	NEPLS Fall at Tufts University
2015	Dependent Types for Real Time Constraints
	ACM Sigplan ML Workshop at ICFP 2015
2015	Integrating SMT into Software Development
	NEPLS Spring at Wesleyan University
2014	Debugging with Types in ATS
	Boston Haskell Meetup
	,

## Service

2024	Secretary for the IEEE Washington D.C. Section
2023	Session Chair for ACM ASIA Conference on Computer and Communications Security
2022	Sub-Reviewer for IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, IEEE European Symposium on
	Security and Privacy
2021	Trojan Horse Award reviewer for the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy
2021	Shadow Program Committee member for the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy
2021	Sub-Reviewer for NDSS, USENIX Security
2020	Sub-Reviewer for ACM CODASPY, DSN, USENIX Security
2019	Sub-Reviewer for ACM CODASPY
2018	Artifact Evaluation Committee member for ACSAC
2018	Sub-Reviewer for ACSAC, RAID, DIMVA, ACM CODASPY
2017	Artifact Evaluation Committee member for ACSAC
2017	Sub-Reviewer for ACM CODASPY

## Teaching

Spring 2021 TF for CS210 Computer Systems

Lectured on fundamentals of UNIX and C programming and helped students with their programming assignments. Over the course of the semester students implemented their own calculator that parsed and evaluated mathematical expressions given in infix notation. Their calculators used reverse polish notation (RPN) as an intermediate representation for simple arithmetic equations.

Fall 2020 TF for CS630 Graduate Design and Analysis of Algorithms

Fall 2019 Lectured on topics including Linear Algebra, LUP Decomposition, Complexity, Approxi-

 $mation \ Algorithms, \ Randomized \ Algorithms, \ and \ Linear \ Programming. \ Managed \ a \ small$ 

team of graders.

Spring 2015 TF for CS111 Introduction to Computer Science

Assisted students through a breadth first introduction to Computer Science that covers programming in Functional, Imperative, and Object Oriented paradigms. Other topics

programming in Functional, Imperative, and Object Oriented paradigms. Other topics such as Computer Organization, Assembly Programming, and Computational Complexity were briefly introduced as well. The class was adapted from the "CS For All" class developed at Harvey Mudd University. My role included leading discussion sections, grading,

and holding office hours.

Spring 2014 TF for CS211 Object Oriented Programming

Assisted students with learning Objective C and writing applications for iOS devices. Students first built familiarity with the iOS environment by gradually constructing a tweeting App in iOS, and then developed their own original apps.

#### Awards

2021	IBM Invention Plateau Award
2020	IBM First Patent Application Award
2020	3rd Place speaker at 7th Annual BU CISE Graduate Student Workshop (CGSW 7.0)
2019	2nd Place speaker at 6th Annual BU CISE Graduate Student Workshop (CGSW 6.0)
2018	Student Travel Award to the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy
2016	Sixth Summer School on Formal Techniques at Menlo College
2015	Verification Mentoring Workshop at the International Conference on Computer Aided
	Verification (CAV)

# Professional Experience

2023-present Senior Member of Technical Staff at Oracle Labs

Investigating language-based security topics within the Graal Platform, including software supply chain security, control-flow integrity (CFI), fuzz testing, binary analysis, and intra-process isolation.

2019-2021 Research Intern at IBM Research, Thomas J. Watson Research Center

Investigated intrusion detection in microservices with the Cyber Security Intelligence (CSI) team. Developed  $\mu$ PolicyCraft, a framework for modeling microservice system call profiles represented as *effect graphs*. Effect graphs are stateful summaries of system call sequences and resources a microservice may interact with during its execution. Policy monitors can then detect policy violations (i.e., intrusions) by looking for deviations from a microservice's effect graph in container telemetry.

2015 Software Engineer Intern at ViaSat

Assisted in developing a business process engine (BPE) that provided a fault tolerant programming framework for executing and managing workflows across distributed systems.

2013 Software Engineer Intern at ViaSat

Investigated how mobile applications received multi-media from content providers by reverse engineering native ARM libraries in Android applications, and using a man-in-the-middle server to augment Javascript applications.

2009-2012 Software Engineer at 829 Studios LLC

Designed, implemented, and deployed OfferedLocal, a web application that allows businesses to run location based advertising campaigns across social networks like Facebook and Twitter. The start-up participated in Mass Challenge and was featured in the Demo Fall 2011 Conference.

Developed and maintained the back office system for the Licensing Industry Merchandisers Association (LIMA), along with an online directory of member companies.

2009-2010 *Technician* at BU Electronics Design Facility

Developed firmware for a medical prototype as part of the FLuorescence-Assisted Resection and Exploration (FLARE) project at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center. The system allowed an external device to control the power output of lasers and regulated their temperature using Peltier coolers. The firmware featured serial communication, analog to digital controllers (ADC) to measure laser temperature, and proportional integral and derivative (PID) controllers to control the Peltier coolers' temperature via pulse width modulation. Assisted in the design, layout, and testing of circuit boards for Physics experiments, including the Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) experiment at CERN.